Delegates allow you to create robust
デリゲートを使うとスクリプトに複雑かつ堅牢な
and complex behaviours in your scripts.
挙動をさせることができます
A delegate can be thought of simply as a container
単純に言い換えると  デリゲートとは関数のコンテナで
for a function that can be parsed around
変数のようにパースさせられる / 扱えるというふうにも
or used like a variable.
言えます
Just like variables, delegates can
デリゲートにも 変数と同様に
values assigned to them
値を割り当てられるほか
and these values can be changed at run-time.
実行時に値を変更することも可能です
The difference is that while variables contain
大きな違いは 変数がデータを格納するのに対し
data delegates contain functions.
デリゲートは関数を格納する点です
Here we have a scene with a game object in it.
さて ここにゲームオブジェクトがひとつ配置されたシーンがあります
The game object has a delegate script attached to it.
このゲームオブジェクトには delegate スクリプトがアタッチされています
We will be monitoring the output of the scene
ではシーンの出力をコンソールビューで
in the console view.
モニターしてみましょう
In the delegate script the first thing we do
delegate スクリプトではまず delegate テンプレートを
is to declare our delegate template.
宣言するところから始めます
This template will dictate exactly what types of
ここで宣言するテンプレートが割り当てられる
methods we can assign to our delegate.
メソットの種類を決定します
We create a delegate with the Delegate keyword.
デリゲートはまず Delegate キーワードで作成します
What follows the delegate keyword is the
そのキーワードに続くのが
delegate's signature. Just like a function
デリゲートの署名です関数と同様に
our delegate has a return type, a name
デリゲートにも  戻り値の型  名前
and a parameter list.
そしてパラメーターのリストがあります
In this example we can see that in
この例では
order for a method to be assigned to this delegate
デリゲートにメソッドを割り当てるには戻り値の型を void とし
it must have a return type of void and
パラメーターは int 型のものひとつと
take a single integer parameter.
しなければなりません
After we create our delegate type we then
デリゲートの型を作り終わったら
declare a member variable.
続いてメンバー変数を宣言します
This member variable has the type of
このメンバー変数は  先ほど作成したデリゲートの
the delegate we just created.
型を持ちます
At the bottom of our script we have two methods,
スクリプトの最後にはさらに 2 つのメソッドがあります
PrintNum and DoubleNum.
PrintNum と DoubleNum です
We can see that each of these methods has a return
両方のメソッドとも  戻り値の型が
type of void and takes a single integer parameter
デリゲートと同様 void でパラメーターは
just like our delegate.
int 型ひとつですね
Additionally, each of these methods does something
しかしこの 2 つのメソッドはパースされた
slightly different with the integer data parsed in.
int データに対して若干異なる処理を行います
Now it's time for us to see
それではデリゲートがどのように
exactly what delegates do.
動作するか実際に見てみることにしましょう
In the Start method you can see that we
Start メソッドではまず
assign the name of our PrintNum method
PrintNum メソッドの名前が
to the myDelegate variable.
myDelegate 変数に代入しました
We then use the myDelegate variable
そして myDelegate 変数を
as if it was a function, and we parse in
関数のように扱い
the value of 50.
値 50 をパースさせます
We then assign the name of the DoubleNum method
続けて DoubleNum メソッドの名前を
to the myDelegate variable.
myDelegate 変数に代入します
Again we call it just like a function.
そして再び関数のように呼び出します
Let's take a look at this code in action.
ではこれを実行するとどうなるか 見てみましょう
Back in Unity we can run our scene
ここで Unity に戻ってシーンを実行し
and look at the console view.
コンソールビューを見てみましょう
We can see that we are able to call 2
同じデリゲート変数を使って 2 つの
different methods using the same
異なるメソッドが呼び出せたことが
delegate variable.
確認できますね
This gives us a lot of power to dynamically
これを活用するとゲーム内で呼び出す関数の
control which functions get called in our game.
動的な制御がとてもやりやすくなります
Delegates also have the ability to be multicast.
またデリゲートはマルチキャストも可能です
Multicasting allows a single delegate variable
マルチキャストすると単一のデリゲート変数で
to represent multiple methods at the same time.
同時に複数のメソッドを示せるようになります
Here we have a scene with an orb in it.
ここにオーブが 1 つ配置されたシーンがあります
The orb has a script called MutlicastScript
オーブには MutlicastScript というスクリプトが
attached to it.
アタッチされています
In our MulticastScript we can see that we have
MulticastScript 内には
created a delegate template.
delegate テンプレートが作成済みです
This template defines a delegate named
このテンプレートで定義されるデリゲートは
MultiDelegate which takes no parameters
名前が MultiDelegate でパラメーターは取らず
and has a return type of void.
戻り値の型は void です
Next we create a member variable
続いて MyMultiDelegate という名前の
named MyMultiDelegate
メンバー変数を作成します
that is of the type of the delegate template
このメンバー変数の型は作成したデリゲートテンプレートの
we just created.
ものになります
At the bottom of our script we have 2
そしてスクリプト下部には 2 つの
methods named PowerUp and TurnRed.
メソッド PowerUp と TurnRed があります
Both of these methods take no parameters
両メソッドともパラメーターは取らず
and have a return type of void,
戻り値の型は void です
just like our delegate type.
デリゲートの型と同じですね
The PowerUp method prints
PowerUp メソッドは画面に
'Orb is powering up' to the screen.
「Orb is powering up」（オーブがパワーアップ中）と出力します
The TurnRed method changes the colour
TurnRed メソッドはオブジェクトの色を
of the object to red.
赤色に変更します
In the start method we will multicast
ここで Start メソッドでデリゲート変数を
our delegate variable.
マルチキャストします
We do this by assigning both the PowerUp method
このとき PowerUp メソッドと TurnRed メソッドは
and the TurnRed method to the same
同じデリゲート変数に対して
delegate variable using the += operator.
+= 演算子を使って代入します
In this way the variable myMultiDelegate
こうすることで変数 myMultiDelegate は
contains both the PowerUp and TurnRed method.
PowerUp メソッドと TurnRed メソッドの両方を含みます
We then call the variable myMultiDelegate
続いて変数 myMultiDelegate を
as if it were a function.
関数のように呼び出します
If we go back in to Unity and run our scene
これで一旦 Unity に戻りシーンを実行してみると
we can see the multicasting our delegate variable
デリゲート変数のマルチキャストが行われ
allowed it to call both the PowerUp
PowerUp と TurnRed の両メソッドが
and the TurnRed methods with a single call.
1 回の呼び出しで行われているのを確認できます
In this manner we were able to
複数の機能をまとめて
stack functionality.
積み重ねられたわけです
If we want to remove a method from a delegate variable
デリゲート変数からメソッドを取り除きたい場合は
we can do so using the -= operator
-= 演算子と
in conjunction with the method's name.
メソッド名を記します
One thing we must be careful of is
なお  何も代入していない状態で
attempting to call a delegate variable like a function
デリゲート変数を関数のように
before we have assigned anything to it.
呼び出さないようにしましょう
Doing so will cause an error
呼び出そうとしてしまうと
and we like to avoid those.
エラーが発生してしまいます
Any delegate variable that doesn't currently
メソッドがひとつも代入されていない状態の
have a method assigned to it will have
デリゲート変数は戻り値として
a value of null.
null を返します
Therefore it is a good idea to always
ですのでデリゲートを使うときは
check to make sure delegate does not equal null
まず null とイコールでないことを確認してからに
before using it.
するとよいでしょう